<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="stylesheet.xsl"?>
<notes>
	<component>
		<!--  ******************************* GENERAL ****************************************** -->
		<name>General</name>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>JMC 8.0 - Major New Release!</title>
			<description>
				This is a major new release of Java Mission Control. The JMC application now requires JDK 11+ to run, but can be used with OpenJDK 8u272+ and
				Oracle JDK 7u40+. It can also open and visualize flight recordings from JDK 7 and 8.  
			</description>
			<image>general/jmc.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Eclipse 4.16 support</title>
			<description>
				The Mission Control client is now built to run optimally on Eclipse 2020-06 and later. To install Java Mission Control into Eclipse, 
				go to the <a href="http://download.oracle.com/technology/products/missioncontrol/updatesites/base/8.0.0/eclipse/">Java Mission Control update site</a>.
			</description>
			<image>general/eclipse.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Supported Plug-ins</title>
			<description>
				There are now several <em>supported</em> plug-ins for use with Java Mission Control. Go to "Install New Software" in Java Mission Control 
				(or Eclipse) to install. If running as plug-ins inside of Eclipse, do not forget to add the 
				<a href="http://jrpgftp.se.oracle.com/jmc/updatesites/supported/8.0.0/eclipse/">update site for supported plug-ins</a>.
			</description>
			<image>general/supported.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Experimental Plug-ins</title>
			<description>
				The JMC team is still sharing <em>experimental</em> plug-ins on the experimental update site. Go to "Install New Software" in Java Mission Control 
				(or Eclipse) to install. If running as plug-ins inside of Eclipse, do not forget to add the 
				<a href="http://jrpgftp.se.oracle.com/jmc/updatesites/experimental/8.0.0/eclipse/">update site for experimental plug-ins</a>.
			</description>
			<image>general/experimental.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Minor bugfixes and improvements</title>
			<description>
				There are hundreds of minor fixes and improvements in this release.
			</description>
			<image>general/bugs.png</image>
			</note>		
		</component>
	
	<!--  ******************************* JFR ******************************* -->

	<component>
		<name>Java Flight Recorder (JFR)</name>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>Automated Analysis of Flight Recordings</title>
			<description>
				Java Mission Control now supports automated analysis of flight recordings. The provided rules and heuristics will help you find troubling functional and 
				performance problems in your application and help provide tuning tips. Some rules that operate with relatively unknown concepts, like safe points, will provide 
				explanations and links to further information. Some rules are parameterized and can be configured to make more sense in your particular environment. Individual 
				rules can be enabled/disabled as you see fit. This is the very first cut - more rules and improved heuristics will be provided as part of JMC updates over time. 
			</description>
			<image>jfr/analysis.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>Running the Automated Analysis Headless</title>
			<description>
				The Mission Control base jars required for the automated analysis are all JDK 7 (and later) compatible, and built to be useable outside of Eclipse. This means that 
				you can perform the automated analysis from the command line. Try running:
				<pre>com.oracle.jmc.flightrecorder.rules.report.JfrRulesReport -min info -format text C:\recordings\JMC-5033\while_installing_from_updatesite.jfr -verbose</pre> 
				when having the following JMC plug-ins on your class path:
				com.oracle.jmc.common, com.oracle.jmc.flightrecorder, com.oracle.jmc.flightrecorder.rules, com.oracle.jmc.flightrecorder.rules.jdk
				If you wish to have the WebLogic Server rules, also add:
				com.oracle.jmc.flightrecorder.ext.wls.parser, com.oracle.jmc.flightrecorder.ext.wls.rules
			</description>
			<image>jfr/textanalysis.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>Use the PDE Plug-in for Creating Custom Rules</title>
			<description>
				It is possible to create custom plug-ins providing one or more rules to participate in the automated analysis of recordings. The easiest way to start creating your 
				own custom rules is to install the PDE plug-in into Eclipse from the <a href="http://jrpgftp.se.oracle.com/jmc/updatesites/experimental/6.0.0/eclipse/">experimental update site</a>.
			</description>
			<image>console/pde.png</image>
		</note>		
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>New Navigation</title>
			<description>
				The navigation between pages has moved from being inside of the JFR editor, to now be in the Outline view. Individual analysis rules can
				be associated with pages, and an overlay on the page icons will show if a rule has found something interesting that relates to a specific page. 
			</description>
			<image>jfr/outline.png</image>
		</note>		
		<note version="6.0">
				<title>New Configurable Stacktrace View</title>
				<description>
					The Stack Trace view has become a separate, configurable, view. When you select something that can be represented as an aggregation of 
					stack traces in the user interface, it will be shown in the Stack Trace view. By default the most commonly taken path will be displayed, 
					and you can switch between branches using the buttons or arrow keys. Should you want to, you can still configure the view to work in 
					the old tree style. By default the tree depth will be reduced by just listing frames vertically until a branch is hit. That too can be disabled
					if you really want to get back to the old style of representing trees. That said, the default style saves a lot of screen estate, and shows the most 
					commonly sought information by default.
				</description>
				<image>jfr/stacktrace.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>Custom Pages</title>
			<description>
				Custom pages can now be created from the Event Browser page. Simply select the event types of interest and click the Create New Page button. 
				The custom page features a filter box at the top which allows you to perform complex filtering. Grouping, sorting and charting can also be 
				accomplished with a few simple context clicks in the view. Once you are happy with the page, it can be exported and shared.
			</description>
			<image>jfr/custompage.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>Stored Selections</title>
			<description>
				It is now possible to focus the user interface on a selection, and to store and re-use the selection in other pages. The selection captures all kinds of aspects 
				associated with the selection, such a the event types, the actual events represented by the selection or the time range spanning the selection. Different selections can be stored,
				and you can switch between them using the selection drop down. You can also select which aspect of the selection you wish for a page to focus on.
				Different pages may chose different default aspects to focus on from a selection, and they may also select an aspect depending on what is in the actual selection.  
			</description>
			<image>jfr/setselection.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The Results View</title>
			<description>
				When the selected page has one or more results associated with it, the Results view will display those results.
			</description>
			<image>jfr/resultsview.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The Properties View</title>
			<description>
				The new Properties view shows the attributes for the current selection, usually one or more events. It is quite useful for setting the focus selection to 
				something very specific, such as the value of the attribute of a specific event.
			</description>
			<image>jfr/properties.png</image>
		</note>		
	</component>
	<component>
		<!--  ******************************* MANAGEMENT CONSOLE ******************************* -->
		<name>Management Console</name>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>Extending the Console</title>
			<description>
				The API for extending the management console has been simplified and improved. The easiest way to see the new API in action is to create a 
				console extension using the Mission Control PDE plug-in inside of Eclipse.
			</description>
			<image>console/pde.png</image>
		</note>
	</component>

	<component>
		<!--  ******************************* Supported Plugins ****************************************** -->
		<name>Supported Plug-ins</name>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The Metadata Plug-in (JFR)</title>
			<description>
				This plug-in shows the metadata available in a recording. This is quite useful when developing rules, as information such as the event type identifiers 
				are typically required. That said, sometimes just looking at the description for an attribute or event type can be helpful to better understand the data.
			</description>
			<image>supported/metadata.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The JavaFX Plug-in (JFR)</title>
			<description>
				This plug-in provides a special page for improved visualization of JavaFX events. It will show information from the pulse logger. For each individual 
				pulse details, such as the name and duration of the phases, will be shown. 
			</description>
			<image>supported/javafx.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The WebLogic Plug-in (JFR)</title>
			<description>
				This plug-in provides a set of pages for analysis of applications deployed in WebLogic Server. A wide range of information is available, such as servlet executions, 
				EJB calls, JDBC calls, JTA transactions and much more. Of course, all that information can be correlated to what is going on in the Java runtime, providing a powerful
				diagnostics and profiling environment for WebLogic Server. This plug-in also contains JFR parser extensions and rules for automated analysis of WLS performance.
			</description>
			<image>supported/wls.png</image>
		</note>
	</component>
	
	<component>
		<!--  ******************************* Experimental Plugins ****************************************** -->
		<name>Experimental Plug-ins</name>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The G1 Plug-in (JFR)</title>
			<description>
				This experimental plug-in shows detailed information about the G1 garbage collector.
				Note: This plug-in only works with JDK 9 recordings.
			</description>
			<image>experimental/g1.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The Usual Suspects</title>
			<description>
				Note that most of the old experimental plug-ins are still available, such as JOverflow (heap waste analysis of hprof dumps), 
				the JMX Console Subscription plug-in (see what is actually fetched), the Flight Recorder Launch Configuration plug-in (control the flight recorder
				as part of launching your apps from within Eclipse), the PDE plug-in (wizards for quickly extending JMC), and more. Since they are not new, they did not 
				get their own entries in this section.
			</description>
			<image>experimental/joverflow.png</image>
		</note>
	</component>
	<!--  ******************************* Bugfixes ****************************************** -->
	<bugfixes>
		<bugfix>
			<area>General</area>
			<synopsis>Better input parsing</synopsis>
			<description>
				Mission Control is now using its framework for physical quantities and units of measurement 
				in more places. This provides a more consistent and coherent way of both entering and visualizing values,
				as well as services like auto completion. 
			</description>
		</bugfix>
		<bugfix>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<synopsis>Can now have more recordings open simultaneously</synopsis>
			<description>
				In previous versions of JMC the entire UI was generated in one go, requiring massive amounts of native UI handles. Now the UI is generated on the fly, 
				making it possible to have more flight recordings open at the same time.
			</description>
		</bugfix>
		<bugfix>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<synopsis>Proper handling of reused OS thread ids</synopsis>
			<description>
				Previous versions of JMC did not handle reused OS thread ids properly. Now such thread id reuse will be handled properly
				as separate threads.
			</description>
		</bugfix>
		<bugfix>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<synopsis>No more clipping problems with large stack traces</synopsis>
			<description>
				The way we rendered stack traces previously could lead to clipping problems when the tree grew quite big.
				The new stack trace view makes it unlikely to encounter the condition when such clipping occurs in the native component.
			</description>
		</bugfix>
		<bugfix>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<synopsis>Will now provide a visual hint if not showing all events</synopsis>
			<description>
				Previously, if there were more events than could fit a table, the table would cut off at a certain number of events. 
				Now the last row of the table will indicate if such a cut off is taking place, as well as show both the limit and how many events would have been available in total. 
				Also, the maximum number of events to show can now be configured in the preferences.
			</description>
		</bugfix>
	</bugfixes>
	<!--  ******************************* Known issues ****************************************** -->
	<knownissues>
		<issue>
			<area>General</area>
			<synopsis>Hibernation and time</synopsis>
			<description>
				After the bugfix of https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-6523160 in JDK 8, the RuntimeMXBean#getUptime() attribute was re-implemented
				to mean "Elapsed time of JVM process", whilst it previously was implemented as time since start of the JVM process. The uptime attribute is used by JMC,
				together with RuntimeMXBean#getStartTime(), to estimate the actual server time. This means that time stamps, as well as remaining time for a flight recording, 
				can be wrong for processes on machines that have been hibernated.
			</description>
		</issue>		
		<issue>
			<area>General</area>
			<synopsis>Tooltip overflow and clipping on OS X with HiDPI screens</synopsis>
			<description>
				The tooltip displayed when hovering over data points or chart elements can be clipped, and the information within is not always possible to read, if you are using a HiDPI monitor
				on OS X. As a workaround, the same information is sometimes available from the Properties view if you first make a selection in the chart.	
			</description>		
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<synopsis>Problem drag-and-dropping recordings to the analysis page</synopsis>
			<description>
				It is possible to drag and drop flight recordings in to Mission Control to open them. However, in JMC 8.0.0, dragging a recording to the Automated Analysis Results page will not work. 
				The Automated Analysis Results page is using a browser component, and that component will be reacting in platform depended ways on drops. A workaround is to drag it to the top of the page or 
				to any other page.
			</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<synopsis>Problem with clipping of tooltips on HiDPI monitors</synopsis>
			<description>
				The tooltip that is displayed when hovering over data points or chart elements 
				can be clipped, and the information within is not always possible to read if you 
				are using a HiDPI monitor. As a workaround, you can sometimes get the same information 
				from the Properties view if you first make a selection in the chart.
			</description>
		</issue>
	</knownissues>
</notes>