<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="stylesheet.xsl"?>
<notes>
	<component>
		<!--  ******************************* GENERAL ****************************************** -->
		<name>General</name>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>JMC 8.0 - Major New Release!</title>
			<description>
				This is a major new release of Java Mission Control. All binary build of the JMC application using the
				Eclipse 2020-09 platform will now require JDK 11+ to run, but can be used with OpenJDK 8u272+ and Oracle JDK 7u40+.
				It can also open and visualize flight recordings from JDK 7 and 8.
			</description>
			<image>general/jmc.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Eclipse 4.16 support</title>
			<description>
				The Mission Control client is now built to run optimally on Eclipse 2020-06 and later. To install Java Mission
				Control into Eclipse, go to the
				<a href="http://download.oracle.com/technology/products/missioncontrol/updatesites/base/8.0.0/eclipse/">Java Mission Control update site</a>
				.
			</description>
			<image>general/eclipse.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Supported Plug-ins</title>
			<description>
				There are now several
				<em>supported</em>
				plug-ins for use with Java Mission Control. Go to "Install New Software" in Java Mission Control
				(or Eclipse) to
				install. If running as plug-ins inside of Eclipse, do not forget to add the
				<a href="http://jrpgftp.se.oracle.com/jmc/updatesites/supported/8.0.0/eclipse/">update site for supported plug-ins</a>
				.
			</description>
			<image>general/supported.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Experimental Plug-ins</title>
			<description>
				The JMC team is still sharing
				<em>experimental</em>
				plug-ins on the experimental update site. Go to "Install New Software" in Java Mission Control
				(or Eclipse) to
				install. If running as plug-ins inside of Eclipse, do not forget to add the
				<a href="http://jrpgftp.se.oracle.com/jmc/updatesites/experimental/8.0.0/eclipse/">update site for experimental plug-ins</a>
				.
			</description>
			<image>general/experimental.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Minor bugfixes and improvements</title>
			<description>
				There are hundreds of minor fixes and improvements in this release.
			</description>
			<image>general/bugs.png</image>
		</note>
	</component>
	
	<!--  ******************************* JFR ******************************* -->
	<component>
		<name>Java Flight Recorder (JFR)</name>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Flame Graph View Improvements</title>
			<description>
				The Flame Graph View is now available in the standard perspective. It can now be configured to be
				rendered either as an icicle graph or a flame graph, and the tool tips have been improved. Click on anything
				representing a selection of events to get the aggregate of stack traces represented by that selection rendered in
				the Flame Graph View.
			</description>
			<image>jfr/flamegraph.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>New Graph View</title>
			<description>
				An early access version of a Graph View is now available. The Graph View will show a directed graph
				where the individual methods are nodes in the graphs, and the edges will represent calls from one method to another.
				The size of the node will represent the "self" contribution, and the thickness of an edge will correlate with the
				number of calls from one method to another in the events. To open up the graph view, go to Window | Show view |
				Other..., then select Mission Control / Graph View. Once the Graph View has opened, it can be docked where you want
				it to be, or dragged out into a new top level window which can be handled by your window manager. Currently there is
				no graph pruning, and large graph will take a very long time to layout and render, during which the UI will freeze.
				Therefore we've imposed a user configurable limit on the number of nodes a graph can have for now.
			</description>
			<image>jfr/graph.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="8.0">
			<title>Predecessors and Successors</title>
			<description>
				The predecessors and successors tabs have been brought back to the Method Profiling page. This means
				that it is now easy to select a method and easily see wherever that method was called from, and to see what was then
				called from that method. This is a temporary solution until we have a separate Butterfly/Sandwich view where any
				selection of a method in a set of events can be rendered in a separately configured view.
			</description>
			<image>jfr/predsucc.png</image>
		</note>
	</component>
	<component>
		<!--  ******************************* MANAGEMENT CONSOLE ******************************* -->
		<name>Management Console</name>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>Extending the Console</title>
			<description>
				The API for extending the management console has been simplified and improved. The easiest way to see
				the new API in action is to create a
				console extension using the Mission Control PDE plug-in inside of Eclipse.
			</description>
			<image>console/pde.png</image>
		</note>
	</component>

	<component>
		<!--  ******************************* Supported Plugins ****************************************** -->
		<name>Supported Plug-ins</name>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The Metadata Plug-in (JFR)</title>
			<description>
				This plug-in shows the metadata available in a recording. This is quite useful when developing rules, as
				information such as the event type identifiers
				are typically required. That said, sometimes just looking at the
				description for an attribute or event type can be
				helpful to better understand the data.
			</description>
			<image>supported/metadata.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The JavaFX Plug-in (JFR)</title>
			<description>
				This plug-in provides a special page for improved visualization of JavaFX events. It will show
				information from the pulse logger. For each individual
				pulse details, such as the name and duration of the phases,
				will be shown.
			</description>
			<image>supported/javafx.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="6.0">
			<title>The WebLogic Plug-in (JFR)</title>
			<description>
				This plug-in provides a set of pages for analysis of applications deployed in WebLogic Server. A wide
				range of information is available, such as servlet executions,
				EJB calls, JDBC calls, JTA transactions and much more.
				Of course, all that information can be correlated to what is
				going on in the Java runtime, providing a powerful
				diagnostics and profiling environment for WebLogic Server. This
				plug-in also contains JFR parser extensions and rules
				for automated analysis of WLS performance.
			</description>
			<image>supported/wls.png</image>
		</note>
	</component>
	<component>
		<!--  ******************************* Agent ******************************* -->
		<name>JMC Agent</name>
		<note version="1.0.0">
			<title>Agent 1.0.0</title>
			<description>
				This is the first version where we build and release the JMC agent. The JMC agent is a byte code
				instrumentation agent, making it easy to declaratively generate JFR events from most methods, even methods for which
				you do not have the source code available. Either configure the agent with an XML configuration field, or use the
				MBean to dynamically change the instrumentation whilst the application is running.
			</description>
			<image>agent/firstrelease.png</image>
		</note>
		<note version="1.0.0">
			<title>Converter Functions</title>
			<description>
				Now any public static method can be used to convert objects of a specific type to one of the types
				supported by flight recorder. The converter to use must be explicitly declared per recorded data.
			</description>
			<image>agent/converters.png</image>
		</note>
	</component>
	<!--  ******************************* Bugfixes ****************************************** -->
	<bugfixes>
		<bugfix>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>5734</bugid>
			<synopsis>Overflow in stacktrace tooltips fixed</synopsis>
			<description>On Mac, the tooltips shown for the stacktraces could overflow. This is now fixed.</description>
		</bugfix>
	</bugfixes>
	<!--  ******************************* Known issues ****************************************** -->
	<knownissues>
		<issue>
			<area>General</area>
			<bugid>4270</bugid>
			<synopsis>Hibernation and time</synopsis>
			<description>
				After the bugfix of https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-6523160 in JDK 8, the
				RuntimeMXBean#getUptime() attribute was re-implemented to mean "Elapsed time of JVM process", whilst it previously
				was implemented as time since start of the JVM process. The uptime attribute is used by JMC, together with
				RuntimeMXBean#getStartTime(), to estimate the actual server time. This means that time stamps, as well as remaining
				time for a flight recording, can be wrong for processes on machines that have been hibernated.
			</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>General</area>
			<bugid>4270</bugid>
			<synopsis>Hibernation and time</synopsis>
			<description>
				After the bugfix of https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-6523160 in JDK 8, the
				RuntimeMXBean#getUptime() attribute was re-implemented to mean "Elapsed time of JVM process", whilst it previously
				was implemented as time since start of the JVM process. The uptime attribute is used by JMC, together with
				RuntimeMXBean#getStartTime(), to estimate the actual server time. This means that time stamps, as well as remaining
				time for a flight recording, can be wrong for processes on machines that have been hibernated.
			</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>7122</bugid>
			<synopsis>Rules evaluation never complete</synopsis>
			<description>Sometimes the rules evaluation may never complete for the GC rules.</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>7071</bugid>
			<synopsis>JMC can't attach to jlinked JVMs</synopsis>
			<description>This one is still under investigation, but it seems JMC can't attach to certain jlinked images.
			</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>7068</bugid>
			<synopsis>JfrRecordingTest (uitest) hangs on the automated analysis page</synopsis>
			<description>Trying to run uitests on Fedora hangs on JfrRecordingTest.</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>7007</bugid>
			<synopsis>Unable to edit run configurations for eclipse project after installing JMC plugin</synopsis>
			<description>Avoid installing the experimental JMC launcher plug-in into Eclipse until this problem has been
				resolved.
			</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>7003</bugid>
			<synopsis>The graph view does not work on Windows</synopsis>
			<description>This is due to a bug in the chromium browser plug-in used by JMC on Windows. See the issue for more
				information.
			</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>6265</bugid>
			<synopsis>JMC crashes with Webkit2+GTK 4</synopsis>
			<description>See the issue for more information.</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>6265</bugid>
			<synopsis>JMC crashes with Webkit2+GTK 4</synopsis>
			<description>See the issue for more information.</description>
		</issue>
		<issue>
			<area>JFR</area>
			<bugid>5412</bugid>
			<synopsis>Dragging and dropping a JFR file into an open analysis page does not work</synopsis>
			<description>The expected behaviour would be to open the recording whenever a file is dropped in the editor area, but
				the behaviour will be defined by the embedded browser component, and not very useful.
			</description>
		</issue>
	</knownissues>
</notes>